Finding Aid for Ludwig Family Papers, 1838-1985, 2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ludwig Family Papers 1838-1985, 2000
Ludwig family.
(in 7 boxes)
6 linear feet (in 7 boxes)
The Ludwig Family Papers document the lives of members of the Ludwig family from the time of their arrival in the United States of America in 1733, through 1985. This collection includes family histories, scrapbooks, and family photographs. Also included in the collection are both personal and professional papers of Claud Cecil Ludwig, Frederick E. Ludwig, and Ruby Newman Ludwig.
85310 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Frederick E. Ludwig in 1976; additional materials were donated by Frederick and Genevive Ludwig in 1998. Donor No. 5786
The collection is open for research.
The Ludwig Family Papers document the lives of members of the Ludwig family since the arrival of Michael and Daniel Ludwig in Philadelphia in 1733. They immigrated to the American colonies from the Palatinate region in Germany. In order to save enough money to bring other family members to America, the brothers established a paper mill and farmed.
Few documents relating to the Ludwig family's experiences in the eighteenth and early part of the nineteenth centuries exist in the collection at the Bentley Historical Library. Fuller documentation begins in 1884 with the birth of Claud Cecil Ludwig on a farm in Sunfield, Michigan. His parents were Warren Edwin Ludwig and Lucinda Sweitzer Ludwig. Claud's early childhood was spent on a farm in Lake Odessa, Michigan. Later the family moved to Portland, Michigan, where Warren Ludwig opened a variety store. Claud worked in the store and attended the Ferris Institute where he studied commercial law. During this period, he also married Ruby Newman. They had three children. In 1911, Claud bought the store which his family had established. Another merchant offered to buy the store in 1913. Claud sold the store and moved to Lansing, Michigan. There he entered the real estate business. He joined the Lansing Real Estate Board and in the following years served as its president. Claud Ludwig also served on the Lansing Chamber of Commerce and the city's Planning Committee. Both he and Ruby Ludwig were active members of their community. They established and taught Sunday School classes for the Baptist Church. During this time, Claud also served on the Y.M.C.A. board at both the city and state level.
Throughout his life, Claud Ludwig was interested in the study of bird life. He spent a considerable amount of time with his family banding birds in the state of Michigan. This interest was passed on to Frederick Ludwig, one of Claud and Ruby's children. He was born in Portland, Michigan, in 1909. Sharing his father's interest in ornithology, Frederick began banding birds while he was in high school. He studied medicine at the University of Michigan, graduating in 1935. Ludwig opened his first office in Port Huron, in 1936. During the same year, he married Genevive Pinson. They had two children, Frederick E. Ludwig II and James Pinson Ludwig.
During World War II, Frederick Ludwig served in the Naval Medical Corps. While stationed in the South Pacific, he developed an odorless method for the treatment of burns. He also collected exotic bird specimens for the University of Michigan Museum.
In 1946, he returned to the United States. He and Genevive started the Birch Creek Orchards in 1947. Over the next five decades, Ludwig continued to practice medicine and to band birds. He banned an average of 2, 000 birds per year.
The Ludwig Family record group covers a period of time from the 1850s to the 1980s. The collection of information documenting the history of the Ludwig family includes family histories, ancestral charts, and a large collection of photographic materials. The diaries and scrapbooks included in the collection describe everyday life during the periods covered. The collection is particularly strong in documenting the lives of Claud Cecil Ludwig and Frederick E. Ludwig.
Subjects:
Baptists--Michigan--Lansing.; Bird banding.; First Baptist Church (Lansing, Mich.); Freemasonry--Michigan.; Ingham County (Mich.); Lansing (Mich.); Ludwig family.; Medicine--Michigan--Port Huron.; Physicians--Michigan--Port Huron.; Port Huron (Mich.); Portland (Mich.); Woman's Christian Temperance Union.; Women--Michigan--Lansing.; World War, 1939-1945.; Ludwig, Frederick Edwin, 1909-; Ludwig, Ruby.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Albion (Calhoun County, Mich.)--Business enterprises.; B.E. Ludwig Store.; Boats.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Albion.; Charlevoix (Mich.); Children.; Families.; Grosse Ile (Mich.); Lansing (Mich.); Ludwig, Frederick Edwin, 1909-; Ludwig family.; Industrial School for Boys (Lansing, Mich.); Michigan State University.; Newman family.; Olds, Ransom Eli, 1864-1950.; Port Huron (Mich.); Portland (Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.; Albums.; Scrapbooks.; Ambrotypes.
- Family Papers 1838-1982
  The Family Papers (.5 linear feet) series contains information about the different branches of the Ludwig family. The collection includes genealogies, histories, letters, and newspaper clippings about the Ludwig and Newman families. A particularly rich resource in this series is a notebook which outlines the history of the Ludwig family since the family first arrived in the United States. Each section of the notebook describes a branch of the Ludwig family, creating a detailed family history.
  - Genealogical Materials 1872-1967
    - Chace/Newman Genealogical Materials 1872-1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Newman Family Ancestral Chart Undated (Box 1)
  - Histories 1858-1967
    - Ludwig Family History 1966 (Box 1)
    - Newman Family History 1858-1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters 1838-1982
    - Chace Family 1838-1982 (Box 1)
    - Powell Family 1877-1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea 1873-1935 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1931-1949 (Box 1)
- Family Scrapbooks 1880s-1960s
  The Family Scrapbooks (1.25 linear feet) series is comprised of scrapbooks containing materials spanning the period between the 1860s and the 1960s. The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings concerning temperance, family activities, and the Baptist Church. They also include greeting cards and photographs. Scrapbook 4 contains articles written about Frederick Ludwig when he was in the Navy, as well as photographs from this period. Another noteworthy item is Scrapbook 7. It contains newspaper clippings and memorabilia from Genevive Ludwig's involvement in the Cancer Crusade in the 1950s.
  - Scrapbook 1 1880s-1960s, gray with maroon corners (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 1860s-1890s, mottled with brown corners (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 3 1930s-1940s, brown, wooden cover (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 4 1940s, blue (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 5 1940s-1960s, red (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 6 1950s, brown leather (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 7 1958, brown (Box 3)
- Family Visual Materials, mid 1800s-1970s
  Individual photographs and six photo albums can be found in the Family Visual Materials (.75 linear feet) series. The photographs include tintypes and ambrotypes. Although some images are unidentified, most of the photographs are portraits of the members and friends of the Ludwig and Newman families. The images found in the photo albums include family pictures as well as images of Portland, Michigan.
  - Albums mid 1800s-1970s
    - Album 1 1900-1960s, 15 1/4 x 11 1/2 in. (Box 3)
    - Album 2 mid 1800s-1960s, 11 1/8 x 9 in. (Box 4)
    - Album 3 early 1900s, 7 x 5 5/8 in. (Box 4)
    - Album 4 1920s-1960s, 8 1/8 x 5 3/4 in. (Box 4)
    - Album 5 1930s-1970s, 12 1/2 x 7 7/8 in. (Box 4)
    - Album 6 1900-1962, 8 1/4 x 11 in. (Box 4)
  - Identified Photographs
    - Chace Family, 11 photographs (Box 4)
    - Early Photographs
      - Aunt Katie Smith (Box 4)
        (retouched tintype)
      - Couple at table (Box 4)
        (framed ambrotype)
      - Grandpa Berrie's Mother (Box 4)
        (tintype)
      - Marcia E. Chace (Box 4)
        (framed ambrotype in case)
      - Mrs. Perritt/Wife of James Chace (Box 4)
      - Uncle Jerome Smith (Box 4)
      - Woman, girl, and man (Box 4)
      - Young woman in paisley dress (Box 4)
    - Ludwig Family, 17 photographs (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 photographs (Box 4)
    - Newman Family, 29 photographs (Box 4)
    - Other Individuals
      - A-F, 9 photographs (Box 4)
      - G-M, 8 photographs (Box 4)
      - N-R, 7 photographs (Box 4)
      - S-Z, 13 photographs (Box 4)
  - Unidentified Photographs
    - Couples, 5 photographs (Box 4)
    - Females, 11 photographs (Box 4)
    - Groups, 8 photographs (Box 4)
    - Males, 12 photographs (Box 4)
- Claud Cecil Ludwig 1916-1971
  The Claud Cecil Ludwig (.25 linear feet) series contains papers reflecting Claud Ludwig's activities in real estate and the Y.M.C.A. Both sub-series contain correspondence pertaining to these activities. One noteworthy item in the Real Estate sub-series is a history of the Lansing Board of Realtors.
  - Certificates and Awards 1920-1957 (Box 4)
  - Real Estate Materials 1916-1968, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Y.M.C.A./Y.W.C.A. Materials 1939-1971 (Box 4)
- Frederick E. Ludwig 1933-1985, 2001
  The Frederick E. Ludwig (2.0 linear feet) series is a rich source of information about the life and activities of Frederick E. Ludwig. It includes information on his activities as a bird bander, his life in the Navy, and his work as a physician. The Personal Papers sub-series includes his autobiography, as well as a manuscript entitled "Out of this World" which describes Frederick Ludwig's experiences in WWII. Papers included in the Professional Papers sub-series pertain to Ludwig's medical practice and his activities as a physician. These include a description of the burn treatment which he developed during WWII. The World War II sub-series consists of essays about his World War II experiences and scores of letters that he wrote to his wife.
  - Personal Papers 1933-1968
    - Autobiographies 1968 (Box 5)
    - Birch Creek Orchards 1958-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Bird Banding 1933-1969, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Remembrance of bird banding and Dr. Max Peet 2001 (Box 5)
    - D.D.T. 1963-1968 (Box 5)
    - Manuscripts 1946-1965
      - "In the Other Examining Room" Manuscript 1960-1965, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - "Out of this War" Manuscript 1946 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Islands National Wildlife Refuge 1967 (Box 5)
  - Professional Papers 1934-1974
    - Academy of General Practice 1954-1967 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1934-1973
      - College of Osteopathic Medicine 1964-1965 (Box 5)
      - Medicare 1960-1974 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1934-1955 (Box 5)
    - Medical Articles Undated (Box 5)
    - Medical Certificates 1936-1966 (Box 5)
    - Michigan State/St. Clair County Medical Societies 1952-1967, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Physicians Art Association 1953 (Box 5)
    - St. Clair County Medical Center 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - St. Clair County Welfare Department 1961-1966 (Box 5)
    - Treatment of Burns 1946 (Box 5)
  - Political Papers 1961-1968
    - Correspondence 1961-1968 (Box 5)
    - George Romney 1964-1969 (Box 5)
    - Proposed Medical Legislation 1962-1968 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan 1930-1985
    - Financial Contributions 1957-1963 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1960-1964 (Box 5)
    - Medical Class of 1935, 1962-1985 (Box 5)
    - Medical School Miscellanea 1930-1932 (Box 5)
    - Regent Candidacies 1958-1964 (Box 5)
  - World War II service
    - Military documents (Box 6)
    - World War II Essays 1943 (Box 6)
    - World War II Letters 1942-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - World War II letters, 5 folders (Box 6)
      (unarranged; letters remain in envelopes)
- Ruby Newman Ludwig 1872-1972
  The Ruby Newman Ludwig (.75 linear feet) series reflects Ruby Newman Ludwig's participation in the First Baptist Women's Society and the Christian Women's Temperance Union. This series also contains her diaries which span the years 1938 to 1972. These serve as a rich source of information about everyday life.
  - First Baptist Church Women's Society 1951-1961 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Agricultural College 1922 (Box 7)
  - Women's Christian Temperance Union 1872-1974 (Box 7)
  - Personal letters (mainly from Claud Ludwig) (Box 7)
  - Diaries 1938-1972, 13 volumes (Box 7)